Phillip: Different organisations will
have different policies and procedures,
but there are some standard principles
that tend to apply everywhere.
As a Team Leader you should be fully aware
of these to be effective in your role.
Maddy: Disciplinary and Dismissal procedures.
When it comes to disciplinary and dismissal
policies, your first responsibility as
a team leader is to take the time to
understand your own organisation’s policies.
Talking to HR or your own manager
is a great place to start.
It’s really important you understand
this because, as a team leader, you’re
likely to be the first person involved
in any disciplinary issues in your team.
ACAS provides standardized policy and process
templates, that lots of organisations use
or refer to, in forming their policies, so
you might want to take a look at them too.
Phillip: Disciplinary procedures are in place
to make sure that everyone respects each other
and their employer’s rules and values, and
that everyone’s work is to the right standard.
Disciplinary procedures aim to solve problems
and prevent them from happening again and
shouldn’t be thought of as ways to punish people.
Maddy: Dismissal procedures
are there as a last resort.
Generally, organisations don’t want
to have to dismiss their people unless
they have to, because it can cause a lot
of disruption and emotional distress.
But there are situations where
dismissal is necessary and unavoidable.
Phillip: Taking the Informal approach
When a disciplinary issue occurs, if possible, the
best way to address it initially is informally.
This saves everyone time and energy.
So, if things aren’t going right for someone
in your team, don’t rush to trigger the
formal disciplinary process right away.
You need to be cautious, patient, and
understanding of everyone involved.
Maddy: Start by arranging to have a private
conversation with the person or people involved.
You shouldn’t go into this with any biases about
who you think is in the right or in the wrong.
That would affect your judgement and
won’t help resolve the situation.
Phillip: Make sure you listen to
everyone’s point of view neutrally.
People will have different opinions
about even simple disciplinary matters,
so it’s really important that you
listen to everyone and stay impartial.
Maddy: Aim to create an agreement about what
changes or improvements need to be made.
If the issue is to do with someone having an
inappropriate attitude at work, you might take
time to find out where this is coming from and
what changes can be made to make this better.
If the disciplinary issue is to do
with performance, you might create a
development plan for the person involved.
The important thing is to focus on finding
ways to improve the situation, not to
pass down judgements and punishments.
Phillip: Time for the Formal Process
When we say that it’s generally better to try
and deal with disciplinary issues informally
first, this doesn’t mean you should try to
sweep difficult issues under the carpet.
Maddy: There are some issues, like bullying,
harassment, discrimination, and other acts of
gross misconduct, where the formal disciplinary
process is the correct one to follow.
This wouldn’t mean you’d abandon all of
the elements of informally tackling the
issue that we’ve described; it just means
you’ve made an appropriate escalation
according to your organisation’s policies.
Phillip: You can see that as a leader it’s very
important that you’re an expert in your own
organisation’s procedures and policies because
members of your team may come to you for advice.
So, remember If you’re ever unsure
of anything, make sure that you
find it out before someone asks you.
That will help you to be in a position
to help your team, as well as knowing how
to navigate these situations yourself.